Guide to the Stuyvesant Morris Pell papers, [ca.1917-1945].
Pell, Stuyvesant Morris papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Stuyvesant Morris Pell papers, [ca.1917-1945].
3459
Pell, Stuyvesant Morris,
4.4 cubic feet.; 9 Mapcase Folders.
{Manuscripts, research materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes lab and lecture notes taken by Pell while at Cornell University, sketches and drawings, thesis and monographs.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Stuyvesant Morris Pell was a specialist in conservation of natural resources and manager of the 16,000 acre range of the Huron Mountain Club in northern Michigan. He was born in New York City and received a B.S. from Cornell in 1939 and an M.S. in 1941. For five years he was warden of the Pleasant Valley Bird and Wild Flower Sanctuary in Lenox, Massachusetts, and he spent one summer as a naturalist and ranger in Acadia National Park, Bar Harbor, Maine.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes lab and lecture notes taken by Pell while at Cornell University with sketches and drawings related to various courses; thesis, monographs, and notes on the common snapping turtle, ca.1939; notebooks with photographs and commentary on wildlife including a "Log of the Pleasant Valley Beaver Colony," 1932, "Log of the Survey of Southern Sanctuaries," 1937, and others from Yosemite Field School, 1939, and from Acadia National Park, Bar Harbor, Maine, 1940; broadsides, brochures, and pamphlets relating to wildlife sanctuaries; prepared biology slides, dissecting kit, and field magnifying lens; original manuscript, carbon copies, and galley proof of SCRIBBLINGS OF AN OUTDOOR BOY, an autobiography; sketches and sketchbooks, pen-and-ink drawings and original watercolor paintings, mostly of birds, wildlife, and camping scenes; also glass slides and photographs of Pell's watercolors, scenes, trips, and wildlife.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Pell, Stuyvesant Morris, 1905-1943.; Pell, Stuyvesant Morris, 1905-1943.; Acadia National Park.; Huron Mountain Club.; Pleasant Valley Bird and Wild Flower Sanctuary.; Yosemite Field School.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources.; Wildlife conservation.; Orithology.; Ornithological illustration.; Conservationists.; Naturalists.; Birds.; Birds in art.
Places:
Bar Harbor (Me.).; Lenox (Mass.).
Form and Genre Terms:
Sketches.; Sketchbooks.; Drawings.; Autobiographies.; Paintings.; Photographs.; Watercolors.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Student Papers
Box 1 and Map case
Coursework
Lecture Notes
Diplomas and Certificates
Series II. Field Work
Boxes 1-2, 4 and Mapcase Folder 7
Field Notes and Notebooks
Informational Materials
Series III. Manuscript and Reprints
Boxes 3 and 4
Series IV. Photographic Materials
Boxes 4-7
Series V. Artwork
Box 4, 9, 10 and Mapcase Folder 1-6 and 8-9
Series VI. Scientific and Art Objects
Box 3 and 8
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Student Papers
  - Coursework
    - Typed Paper: "An Analysis of the Food Habits and Preliminary Ecological Study of the Common Snapping Turtle", 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Carbon copy of M.S. Thesis, "Notes on the Habits on the Common Snapping Turtle, Chelydra Serpentina (Linn.) in Central New York" (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Turtle Problems - Field Notebook., April-December 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Turtle Problems - Notes, Articles and Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Thesis "Notes on the Habits on the Common Snapping Turtle, Chelydra Serpentina (Linn.) in Central New York" (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Zoology Department (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Wilson Ornithological Club Program, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes correspondence and notes
  - Lecture Notes
    - Mammology (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
    - Aquatic Plants (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Forestry, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Aquatic Insects, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Game Management, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - Zoology (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Invertebrate Zoology, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 18-22)
    - Algae, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - Botany, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 25, 27-34)
    - Biology (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Nature Study Teaching, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Entomology, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 36-38)
    - Ornithology, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 39-43)
    - Economic Entomology, c.1939 (Box 1, Folder 44-46)
  - Diplomas and Certificates
    - Diploma from St. Mark's School, 1923 (Folder 7)
    - Diploma from Cornell University, College of Agriculture, B.S., 1939 (Folder 7)
    - Diploma from Cornell University, M.S., 1941 (Folder 7)
    - Certificate from Phi Kappa Phi, 1938 (Folder 7)
- Series II. Field Work
  - Field Notes and Notebooks
    - "Log of the Pleasant Valley Beaver Colony" by S.M. Pell (Box 1, Folder 47-49)
      Includes photographs
    - Notes, scrapbook, check lists, talks at Yosemite Field School, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
      Scrapbook includes photographs.
    - Notes taken on Acadia National Park, Bar Harbor Maine, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Pell had a temporary summer job here. Includes photographs.
    - Log of the Survey of Southern Sanctuaries (Box 4)
    - 2 small note books with bird records, c. 1917-1920 (Box 4)
    - 1 small note book (Box 4)
  - Informational Materials
    - Copy of "Report on Wildlife Studies at the Huron Mountain Club 1939-1942" by Richard Manville, August, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Waterfowl Bulletins, U.S. Department of the Interior, Bureau of Biological Survey and Department of Agriculture, 1915-1940 (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
      Mimeograph and printed materials
    - Handwritten Notes (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Bird Breeding in Several States, Canada and the West Indies. Conservation Legislation in Congress. Notes on plants and animal life
    - Summer 1937 and Miscellaneous, c. 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      "Field Mice (Genus Microtus;) Their Economic Status and Their Natural Enemies" by S. Morris Pell. Notes, maps and articles.
    - National Park Service, Predator Policy, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Also "Death and Transfiguration in Delaware" by William Vogt, National Association of Audubon Societies regarding mosquito control
    - Acadia National Park Materials, 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Includes fabric swatches for U.S. National Park Service Uniforms and Shirts
    - 2 copies of Huron Mountain Club map, Marquette County, Michigan by S.M. Pell modified after, 1942 (Folder 4)
    - 2 copies of Snipe Shooter's map of Shinnecock Bay, Long Island with annotations (Folder 4)
    - 6 posters advertising lectures by S. Morris Pell and 2 posters advertising the Pleasant Valley Bird and Wild Flower Sanctuary (Folder 5)
- Series III. Manuscript and Reprints
  - Scribblings of an Outdoor Boy: Being the Reminiscence of Stuyvesant Morris Pell, Up to the Year 1943 when, Having Reached the Age of 38 Years He Came to a Great Adventure with Life; 1945 (Box 3, Folder 1-11)
    Correspondence, original typed manuscripts, 2 carbon copies, and galley proofs.
  - Scribblings of an Outdoor Boy: Being the Reminiscence if Stuyvesant Morris Pell, Up to the Year 1943 when, Having Reached the Age of 38 Years He Came to a Great Adventure with Life, 1945 (Box 4)
    Finished Printed Book
  - Bird Lore, 1938 (Box 4)
    Cover by Pell
- Series IV. Photographic Materials
  - Two Loose Photographs - Beavers (Box 4)
  - Postal Views (Box 4)
  - Wooden Box of 4"x3.25" glass plate slides (Box 5)
    167 plants, birds, and countryside scenes. For both Box 5 and 6 many of these sides were issued by the Department of Public Education, Museum of Natural History (NYC). Others bear the name of Edward Van Altena, 71-79 W. 45th Street, NYC.
  - 4"x3.25" glass plate slides (Box 6)
  - 35mm color slides (Box 6)
  - Pell duck banding (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Dr. Loncope Housatonic River (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Sanctuary scenes (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Sanctuary Ducks (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Sanctuary Birds (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Sanctuary Beaver (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Lenox trips (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Sanctuary pictures (except apartment) (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Beaver drawings for children's story (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Sanctuary (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Duck backgrounds and watercolors (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Lecture Slides (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Pittsfield trout hatchery (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Charleston with W.P., 1935 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Charleston, with K.L.W., 1936 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Southern Trip - Birds, Great White Heron, Mallards, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Southern Trip - Refuge Work, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Southern Trip - Soil Erosion, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Southern Trip - Ducktown, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Southern Trip - Various, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Penikese Island and Ithaca, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Applied Ornithology (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Trips - Cape May, Sweet Briar, and Yosemite, 1938-1939 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Negatives for Pell High trip (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Negatives for Yosemite Valley Research Reserve (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Yosemite trips out (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Yosemite trips (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Arcadia, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Negatives for Huron Mountain (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Negatives for Huron Mountain (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Huron Mountain (Box 7, Folder 31)
- Series V. Artwork
  - Sketch book of bird and camping scenes, c. 1918 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook (Box 4)
  - 11 small sketchbooks (Box 4)
  - 23 watercolor paintings by Stuyvesant Morris Pell (Box 9)
  - "The Tale of Almeek the Beaver" by S. Morris Pell (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - 55 Folio of watercolors and pencil drawings, c. 1928-1931 (Folder 1)
  - 17 Folio of charcoal drawings of animals (Folder 2)
  - 13 Folio of life drawings (Folder 3)
  - 4 30"x22" watercolor renderings on boards (Folder 4)
  - 1 16"x11" pen and ink color wash of the skeleton of Nyroca vallisneria, with skull of Nyroca marila (Folder 5)
  - 2 pen and ink drawings of ducks (Folder 5)
  - 3 painted posters for events (Folder 5)
  - 1 16"x11" pen and ink rendering of Procellariiform profiles (beaks) (Folder 5)
  - 14 15"x11" watercolor renderings of birds on boards (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
  - 3 mounted watercolors of birds, 1931 (Folder 6)
  - 3 mounted watercolors of birds and 1 of horses, 1931 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 62 prints of pen and ink drawings of birds, waterfowl and hunting scenes (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - 24 charcoal and crayon sketches of birds, fish etc. on brown paper (Folder 8)
  - 23 charcoal and crayon sketches of birds, fish etc. on brown paper (Folder 9)
- Series VI. Scientific and Art Objects
  - Case of prepared biology slides (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 3 envelopes dissecting kits (Box 3, Folder 13-15)
  - Field magnifying glass with box (Box 8)
  - Dissecting kit in wooden box (Box 8)
  - 2 printing blocks for cover of "Bird Lore" designed by Pell (Box 8)